Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tape 348, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 348)
  Side A: This tape includes a program of Descubriendo la verdad, another program of the CID. First they narrate the biography of Carlos Diago, an activist against Batista that was subsequently sub-secretary of the economy in Castro's government. He went into exile in Puerto Rico in 1962 and worked with Manolo Ray in several pro-democracy groups against Castro. He is now a professor of tourism in a university in Puerto Rico and has declared himself an active sympathizer of the CID. In this program Diago talks about the failure of tourism in Cuba, which 32 years was the top vacation destination in the Caribbean. Previously tourism was based on private investment, now it is based on foreign investment. It paralyzes the economy because the hotel chains are only charging one third of what a room in the hotel is actually worth. Now tourism is controlled by the mafias and the only Cuban people that can participate in it either have dollars or are prostitutes. Tourism is also destroying the country's environment and natural resources.
  Side B: This tape contains another segment of Descubriendo la verdad. A group of guests ask questions of Professor Diago. They cover the following themes in detail and with many statistics: a comparison of tourism in Cuba and in other Caribbean countries; cruise ship routes throughout the Caribbean; the prevalence of the dollar in Cuba; the possibility of recovering a lucrative tourism industry post-Castro; who are the major tourist groups that visit Cuba; the pejorative effects of Castro's government on tourism; the political crisis in Haiti and its similarities with the situation in Cuba; the rejection of the Chinese model of labor and privatization; and the lasting effects of the embargo.
  Side A: Esta cinta consta de un programa de Descubriendo la verdad, otro programa del CID. Aquí cuentan la biografía de Carlos Diago, un activista contra Batista que fue sub-secretario de economía en el gobierno de Castro. Se exilió de Cuba a Puerto Rico en 1962 y trabajó con Manolo Ray en varios grupos pro-democracia contra Castro. Ahora es profesor de turismo en una universidad en Puerto Rico y se ha declarado simpatizante activo del CID. En este programa Diago habla del fracaso del turismo en Cuba, que hace 32 años era el primer destino turístico del Caribe. El turismo antes se basaba en la inversión personal, ahora se basa en la inversión extranjera. Paraliza la economía porque las compañías hoteleras suelen cobrar por habitación tres veces menos que lo que vale. Ahora el turismo está controlado por las mafias y los únicos cubanos que participen en el turismo o tienen dólares o son prostitutas. El turismo también está destruyendo el medio ambiento del país.
  Side B: Consta de otro programa de Descubriendo la verdad. Ahora algunos invitados le hacen preguntas al profesor Diago. Tratan los siguientes temas en detalle y con evidencia estadística: la comparación del turismo en Cuba con el de los otros países caribeños; las rutas de cruceros por el Caribe; la prevalencia del dólar en Cuba; la posibilidad de recuperar un turismo rentable post-Castro; quiénes son mayormente los turistas que van a Cuba; los efectos peyorativos del castrismo en el turismo; la crisis política en Haití y las semejanzas con la situación en Cuba; el repudio al modelo chino y a la privatización; y los efectos del embargo.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 349, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 349)
  Side A: A phone interview with Alfredo Melero and Yndamiro Restano for Al cantío de un gallo. Restano says that in Paris, he interviewed the First Lady of France, Danielle Mitterrand, who had helped him get out of jail in Cuba. He also mentions that UNESCO has given him support in his fight against the Castro regime. Melero then explains the name of the show, saying that both he and Carlos Franqui have their roots in the country, so they chose a popular saying to indicate that Cuba is only a rooster's crow (a very short time) away from freedom.
  Side A: Una entrevista telefónica entre Alfredo Melero e Yndamiro Restano para Al cantío de un gallo. Restano cuenta que en París entrevistó a la primera dama de Francia, Danielle Mitterrand, quien lo había ayudado a salir de la cárcel en Cuba. También menciona que la UNESCO le ha dado su apoyo en su lucha contra el régimen de Castro. Melero explica el nombre del programa, diciendo que tanto él como Carlos Franqui son de origen campesino, así que escogieron un dicho popular para indicar que Cuba está "al cantío de un gallo" de la libertad.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 350, 1 (Box 350)
  Duplicate of Tape 177/Copia de Tape 177.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 351, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 351)
  Side A: Carlos Franqui reads an interview with Sebastián Arcos, a leader of the opposition who has recently been released from prison, titled "Fidel Castro is a mastermind of evil." In the interview, Arcos discusses politics and life as a Cuban prisoner. Carlos Franqui is traveling throughout Europe with his family, but he still is involved with the resistance and he gives some news from Europe. He relates that some Cuban dissidents were invited to speak in France, but the Cuban government did not allow their participation, a clear sign of their fear of free expression. Franqui is working with many organizations in Italy regarding international human rights, and has recently met with the president of the constitutional affairs committee, Gustavo Selva. Alfredo Melero introduces an exiled Cuban who is going to explain the experience of being an exile to the Cuban listeners who remain in Cuba. He says that he expected to find a lot of hostility in the outside world, because ever since he was young in Cuba he was indoctrinated to believe in the evils of capitalism. When he was in Cuba he studied and worked for years, but he could not even afford to buy his kids a bottle of Coke, which is why he left the country. In exile, he discovered that Cubans still retain their Cubanness- they are simple and hardworking.
  Side B: Outside of Cuba, commercials sell cereal, cars and other products, but within Cuba health and education are the main topics of commercials. The government uses these two topics as propaganda, altering the data to improve their public image. Achievements in health have mostly been qualitative – now there are more doctors distributed across the country. However, many hospitals and medical centers lack proper medicine, and there are separate hospitals for wealthy and underprivileged citizens. Melero contrasts this to the US health care system, where most employers offer health insurance to cover costs, and there is more choice about what type of health care people can receive. In short, the revolution improved too little about the Cuban health care system at too high a cost.
  Side A: Carlos Franqui lee una entrevista con Sebastián Arcos - líder de la oposición que acabó de salir de la cárcel - titulada "Fidel Castro es un genio del mal." En la entrevista, Arcos habla sobre la política y la vida en una cárcel cubana. Carlos Franqui está viajando por Europa con su familia, pero sigue involucrado con la resistencia y da algunas noticias desde Europa. Relata que algunos disidentes cubanos fueron invitados a dar discursos en Francia, pero el gobierno cubano suspendió la participación de éstos en una clara señal del miedo a la libre expresión. Franqui está trabajando con muchas organizaciones en Italia acerca de los derechos humanos internacionales, y acaba de tener una reunión con el presidente de la comisión de asuntos constitucionales, Gustavo Selva. Alfredo Melero presenta a un exiliado cubano que va a hablar en Al cantío de un gallo para explicar la experiencia de ser un exiliado a los cubanos que permanecen en Cuba. Dice que lo que esperaba encontrar en el exilio era mucha hostilidad porque desde que era joven en Cuba fue indoctrinado a creer en el mal del capitalismo. En Cuba, estudió y trabajó por años pero ni siquiera podía comprarles una Coca-Cola a sus hijos y por lo tanto salió del país. En el exilio ha descubierto que los exiliados mantienen su cubanía a la medida que son sencillos y trabajadores.
  Side B: En el exterior hay anuncios para cereal, carros y otros productos, pero en Cuba los anuncios se tratan de la salud y la educación. El gobierno emplea estos dos temas como propaganda, alterando las cifras para mejorar su imagen pública. Los logros en el campo de la salud han sido mayoritariamente cuantitativos, es decir, hay más médicos distribuidos por todo el país. Sin embargo, a muchos hospitales y consultorios les faltan recursos como las medicinas adecuadas, y existen hospitales separados para la gente adinerada y los pobres. Melero contrasta este sistema al de EEUU, en que los empleadores proveen a los trabajadores del seguro médico para pagar los costos, y hay más oportunidades para escoger el tratamiento que uno quiere. En resumen, la revolución no mejoró mucho el sistema de salud cubano y por un precio demasiado alto.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 352, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 352)
  Side A: Franqui describes how Fidel mix very different political ideologies to create the system that has been implemented in Cuba for decades. He talks about how the Cuban revolution was the subject of the socialists as the ideal model of the communist ideology but later proved a disappointment. He mentions the conflict between the socialist Latin American and Cuban dissidents. Franqui mentioned how he attempted to change things on the island for decades instead of simply perusing the course of saving his own life. But eventually he describes how he left Cuba after coming to the conclusion that he was not going to change the regime from within. He also became disillusioned.
  Side B: Franqui continues by describing his time in Italy after leaving Cuba and adjusting to living somewhere else. Franqui also describes how Fidel offered to resign in 1958 by different ideology with the president of the movement against Batista but I get to keep the people by acclamation.
  SIde A: Franqui describe la manera en que Fidel mezclo ideologías políticas muy diferentes para crear el sistema que ha implementado en Cuba durante las ultimas décadas. Habla de la manera en que la revolución Cubana fue el sujeto de los socialistas como el modelo ideal del comunista ideal pero que pronto llego a desilusionar. Menciona el conflicto entre los socialistas Latino Americanos y los disidentes Cubanos. Franqui menciona como el atento de cambiar las cosas en la isla en vez de salvarse su propia vida. Pero describe la manera en que el dejo a Cuba después de que llego a concluir que el no iba poder cambiar ideología Castrista desde adentro. El también se desilusionó.
  Side B: Franqui sigue describiendo su tiempo en Italia después de dejar a Cuba. Franqui también describe como Fidel ofreció a resignar en el 1958 por diferentes de ideología con el Presidente del movimiento contra Batista pero llego a mantenerlo por aclamación del pueblo.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 353, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 353)
  Side A: The program describes the pressure that Cuban dissidents have exerted over the international community to renounce Castro government violations of human rights. They attended a conference in Geneva in which the Western European countries denounced the Castro government for its treatment of political prisoners. A description of the reactions of the international community. They achieved something in between—Cuba will be required to report annually to the Secretary General of the United Nations on the subject of human rights.
  Side B: The group that attended the conference in Geneva answer questions about the pressure being exerted on the international community. A major question they answer is that the journalists want to know why most of this pressure comes from Cubans outside the island. They explain that is the result of censorship that the government has on the Cuban people that thereby requires that human rights be represented by exiles no longer on the island or in danger of being coerced by the government.
  Side A: El programa describe la presión que los disidentes cubanos han ejercido hacia la comunidad internacional para que renuncian las violaciones del gobierno Castrista sobre los derechos humanos. Atendieron una conferencia en Ginebra en que los países occidentales Europeos denunciaron el gobierno de Castro por su tratamiento de los presos políticos. Es una descripción de las reacciones de la comunidad internacional. Se logro algo en el medio—Cuba va tener que reportar anualmente al Secretario General de las Naciones Unidas sobre el sujeto de derechos humanos.
  Side B: El grupo que atendió la conferencia en Ginebra responda preguntas sobre la presión que están ejerciendo sobre la comunidad internacional. En particular responden a una pregunta en que el periodista quiere saber porque la mayoría de esta presión viene de cubanos fuera de la isla. Ellos explican que es resultado de la censura que el gobierno tiene sobre el pueblo Cubano requiere que el exilio represente los derechos humanos en la isla.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 354, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 354)
  Side A: Franqui describes the origin of Camilo Cienfuegos. He discusses how colonial Spain was the enemy of Cuba and exploited the island for close to four hundred years. He describes the change in 1902 when many Spanish began migrating to the island. Franqui describes a brief history of the youth of Camilo Cienfuegos and his families of Spanish origin and the events that came to form him into a revolutionary later on in life.
  Side A: Franqui describe el origen de Camilo Cienfuegos. Habla sobre la manera en que España colonial fue enemigo de Cuba que exploto a la isla por los últimos cuatrocientos años. Describe que esto cambio en 1902 cuando muchos Españoles comenzaron a emigrar a la isla. Franqui describe una breve historia de la juventud de Camilo Cienfuegos y su familia de origen Española y los eventos que llegaron a formarlo como un revolucionario.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 355, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 355)
  Side A: Franqui introduces Ismael Suárez de la Paz who was one of the coordinators of the 26 of June Movement and was very close to Castro in the years of the revolution. Franqui asks details of Castro's personality to know more about the dictator and how to overthrow him. Suarez describes how he became disillusioned by the Revolution as he got to know Castro better. Suarez describes how Castro is an absolute mess in his knowledge of how economic systems work. Suarez points out Castro's stubbornness' and how he refuses to change course even when he knows that he is wrong.
  Side A: Franqui introduce a Ismael Suárez de la Paz que era uno de los Cubanos que era coordinador del Movimiento 26 de junio que era muy cercano a Castro en los años de la revolución. Franqui le pregunta detalles de la personalidad de Castro para poder saber mas sobre el dictador para saber como ganar contra el. Suárez menciona como el se decepciono de la revolución después de acercarse mas a Fidel. Suárez describe que Fidel es un desastre un su conocimiento de la manera en que funciona una economía. Suárez hace un caso de la obstinación de Castro y que el es un hombre que jamás abandonara su camino.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 356, CCirca 1994-1998; 1 (Box 356)
  Side A: Franqui talks about Fidel Castro's old age and how this will affect his government. He also mentions a visit that Fidel recently made to French President Mitterrand. Franqui mentions that Mitterrand is a man in the last days of his power and violating the opinion of the people he serves. Franqui talks about the relationship between omniscient Marxism as a model and that system that Fidel has implemented on the island. They go onto talk about Dr. Levi Marrero talks one of the most important Cuban intellectuals.
  Side B: Melero and Franqui continue to talk about the recently deceased Dr. Levy Marrero an important economist and geographer. They read a piece by Marrero about how Cuba was recovered after the devastation of two wars against Spanish colonialism. Marrero said that with the help of the exile community in the United States, Cuba will be able to recover quickly when the contemporary government is expelled. Marrero mentions the importance of an eternal Cuba that is to be rebuilt when the totalitarian Castro government is overthrown. Melero read another article in which Marrero describes the reconcentration suffered by the Cuban people during the 1898 War for Independence. Marrero writes about how that the island was devastated after 1899 and came to new heights after something that can happen again.
  Side A: Franqui habla sobre la vejez de Fidel Castro que esta llegando a tener una edad muy avanzada. También menciona una visita de Fidel a el Presidente Frances Mitterrand. Franqui menciona que Mitterrand es un hombre en los últimos días de su poder y violando la opinión del pueblo que el sirve. Franqui habla sobre la relación entre Castro el modelo de marxismo omnisciente que el a implementado en la isla. Habla sobre el Doctor Levi Marrero un intelectual importante Cubano cuyo produjo muchos libros sobre la economía y sociedad de la isla.
  Side B: Franqui y Melero continúan hablando sobre el recientemente fallecido Doctor Levy Marrero un economista y geógrafo. Leen un relato sobre la manera en que Cuba se recupero después de las devastaciones de las dos guerras contra el colonialismo Español. Marrero dice que con la ayuda de la comunidad del exilio en los Estados Unidos va poder recuperarse rápidamente cuando el gobierno contemporáneo es expulsado. Marrero menciona la importancia de la Cuba eterna que va poder ser reconstruida cuando se acabe el gobierno totalitario Castrista. Melero leyó otro articulo de Marrero que describe que la reconcentración sufrida por el pueblo cubano durante la guerra de independencia de 1898. Marrero menciona que la isla estaba mucho mas devastada después del 1899 y que llego a nuevas alturas después—algo que puede pasar otra vez.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 357, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 357)
  Side A: Melero introduces the journalist Andres Reinaldo who conducts an interview of Carlos Franqui. Franqui mentions the need to revisit the Cuba's history that has been lost during the decades of the Castro government. Reinaldo asks Franqui how he came to see that the revolution was being hijacked by Castro's own interests. Franqui mentions that his main problem came to who had the power. What bothered Franqui most was the transfer of power from the wealthy classes to Castro instead of the people. Franqui described Fidel as the leader of the world's largest estate—the whole island. The Revolution simply supplanted American interests with those of the Russians and those of the wealthy landed elite with government stooges. The revolution served to create a new oligarchy rather than to help the people.
  Side B: Reinaldo continues to interview Carlos Franqui. Franqui mentions that Cuba is bound to reach a critical stage of revolution as in Poland and Hungary and that the Russians are not going to be able to help in this case. Franqui goes on to describe the failure of the revolution and how it has been received by the different groups in exile. To Franqui, he contributed to a dismal failure. Franqui mentions that the future of a prosperous Cuba is to let individuals have more independence in work and economy and to determine their own futures.
  Side A: Melero introduce el periodista Andrés Reinaldo que entrevista a Carlos Franqui. Franqui menciona la necesidad de revisitar la historia cubana que a sido perdida durante las décadas del gobierno Castrista. Reinaldo le pregunta a Franqui como el llego a ver que la revolución estaba siendo secuestrada por los intereses Castrista. Franqui menciona que el problema fundamental llego en quien tenia el poder. Cuando esto llego de transferirse a Castro en vez del pueblo desde las clases ricas. Franqui describe a Fidel como el líder de la latifundio mas grande del mundo. En efecto el sistema a reemplazado el Americano con el Ruso y la clase rica con peones del gobierno. La revolución sirvió para crear una oligarquía nueva en vez de una para ayudar el pueblo.
  Side B: Reinaldo continua su entrevista de Carlos Franqui. Franqui habla que Cuba va llegar a un nivel critico de revolución como en Polonia y Hungría y que los rusos no van a poder ayudar en este caso. Franqui sigue describiendo el fracaso de la revolución y la manera en que es recibido por los diferentes grupos del exilio. Para Franqui es un fracaso triste cuyo el contribuyó. Franqui menciona que el futuro de una Cuba prospera esta en dejar que los individuos tengan mas independencia en trabajo y economía y poder determinar sus propios futuros.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 358, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 358)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui talk about the visit of Foreign Minister Ricardo Alarcon to Washington and whether this represents tremendous changes that might be coming to the island. Franqui speculates about Fidel's health and the implications that this visit discerns. Franqui mentions that Fidel's only guiding principal is that of maintaining power as long as possible. Franqui's more interested in the actions that the Cuban people will take. Montijo says that Fidel is not likely to leave power anytime soon and that his end will only come from self-destruction. Castro will end his own life when he accepts his failures. They talk about the power dynamics between the triumvirate of Fidel, Raul and Alarcón.
  Side B: Franqui continues discussing the position of Ricardo Alarcón and his visit to Brazil. They speculate about the fact that Raul will not be Fidel's likely successor. They also speculate that Casto's government is likely dealing with a health or political crisis internally. Franqui thinks that Castro is replicating Mao Zedong in giving the appearance of a slow retirement form power when in fact he will continue holding onto the reins of power from behind the scenes. They speculate that Castro's absence at the Brazilian inauguration has to do with this political or health crisis in Havana because Brazil is a crucial ally of the Castro regime; such an absence is not something to be taken lightly. Montijo mentions that it is likely that some internal change is happening on the island due to the economic crisis that is occurring. She thinks that future changes will only be superficial in order to have the effect of looking like significant changes.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui hablan sobre la visita de Ministro de Asuntos del Exterior Ricardo Alarcón a Washington y si indica un cambio tremendo que debe estar llegando a la isla. Franqui especula sobre la salud de Fidel y las implicaciones que esta visita discierne. Franqui menciona que Fidel no tiene consciencia que el no tiene solo el principio de mantener poder por el máximo tiempo. Franqui la interesa mas lo que va ser el pueblo. Montijo menciona que Fidel no se va y que solamente se acaba Fidel con su autodestrucción. Castro va acabar su propia vida cuando acepta sus fracasos. Hablan sobre la dinámica de poder entre el triunvirito de Fidel, Raúl y Alarcón.